<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The laws and acts of the second Parliament, of our most high and dread soveraign, Charles the Second by the grace of God, King of Scotland, England, France and Ireland, defender of the faith begun at Edinburgh, the 19. of October, 1669. By a noble Earl, John Earl of Lauderdail, Viscount Maitland, Lord Thirlestane, and Bolton, &amp;c. His Majesties Commissioner for holding the same, by vertue of a commission under His Majesties Great Seal of this kingdom: with the special advice and consent of the Estates of Parliament. Extracted from the records of Parliament, be Sir Archibald Primerose of Chester, knight and barronet, clerk to His Majesties Council, Registers and Rolls.</title>
            <title>Acts.</title>
            <author>Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829514</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829514</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33954</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58642)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33954)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1980:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The laws and acts of the second Parliament, of our most high and dread soveraign, Charles the Second by the grace of God, King of Scotland, England, France and Ireland, defender of the faith begun at Edinburgh, the 19. of October, 1669. By a noble Earl, John Earl of Lauderdail, Viscount Maitland, Lord Thirlestane, and Bolton, &amp;c. His Majesties Commissioner for holding the same, by vertue of a commission under His Majesties Great Seal of this kingdom: with the special advice and consent of the Estates of Parliament. Extracted from the records of Parliament, be Sir Archibald Primerose of Chester, knight and barronet, clerk to His Majesties Council, Registers and Rolls.</title>
                  <title>Acts.</title>
                  <author>Scotland.</author>
                  <author>Primrose, Archibald, Sir, 1616-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>44 , [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>re-printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson, printer to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum privilegio.</note>
                  <note>Includes a list of the Acts not printed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Law --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33954:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAWS AND ACTS OF THE SECOND PARLIAMENT, Of our moſt High and Dread SOVERAIGN, CHARLES THE SECOND, By the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>Scotland, England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith</p>
            <p>Begun at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the 19. of <hi>October,</hi> 1669.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Noble Earl,</hi> John <hi>Earl of</hi> Lauderdail, <hi>Viſcount</hi> Maitland, <hi>Lord</hi> Thirleſtane, <hi>and</hi> Bolton, <hi>&amp;c. His Majesties Commiſſioner for holding the ſame, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of a</hi> COMMISSION <hi>under His Majeſties Great Seal of this Kingdom:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the ſpecial Advice and Conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Extracted from the Records of Parliament, be Sir <hi>ARCHIBALD PRIMEROSE</hi> of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Knight and Barronet, Clerk to His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Council, Regiſters and Rolls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Re-Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to the Kings Moſt Excellent <hi>Majeſty, Anno Dom.</hi> 1679.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M PRIVELEGIO.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:33954:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>CR</p>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="acts">
            <pb facs="tcp:33954:2"/>
            <head>LAWS and ACTS made in the ſecond <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> our our most High and Dread Soveraign, <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second, by the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>Scotland, England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland, Defender of the Faith.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>I. <hi>ACT aſſerting His</hi> Majeſties <hi>Supremacy over all Perſons and in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>November</hi> 16. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Eſtates of Parliament having ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidered, how neceſſar it is, for the good and Peace of the Church and State, That His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Power and Authority, in relation to Matters and Perſons Eccleſiaſtical, be more clearly aſſerted by an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Have therefore thought fit it be Enacted, Aſſerted and Declared, Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with Advice and Conſent of His Eſtates of Parliament, do hereby Enact, Aſſert and Declare, That His <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath the Supreme Authority and Supremacy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33954:3"/>over all Perſons and in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical within this His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that by vertue thereof, the Ordering and Diſpoſal of the External Government and Policy of the Church doth properly belong to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and His Succeſſors, as an inherent Right to the Crown: And that His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and His Succeſſors may Settle, Enact and Emit ſuch Conſtitutions, Acts, and Orders, concerning the Adminiſtration of the External Government of the Church, and the Perſons imployed in the ſame, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Eccleſiaſtical Meetings, and Matters to be propoſed and determined therein, as they in their Royal Wiſdom ſhall think fit. Which Acts, Orders and Conſtitutions, being recorded in the Books of Council and duly publiſhed, are to be obſerved and obeyed by all His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects, any Law, Act or Cuſtom to the contrary notwithſtanding. Likeas, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> with Advice and Conſent foreſaid, doth Reſcind and Annull all Laws, Acts and Clauſes thereof, and all Cuſtoms and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, Civil or Eccleſiaſtick, which are contrary to, or inconſiſtent with His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Supremacy as it is hereby aſſerted, And declars the ſame void and null in all time coming.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33954:3"/>
               <head>II. <hi>ACT concerning the Militia.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>November</hi> 16. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as by divers ancient Laws an Acts of Parliament, made in the Reigns of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royal Anceſtors, it is Statute and Ordained, That Weapon-ſhowings be holden in ilke Shire ſeveral times in the year, at which the Lieges are appointed to be harniſhed and armed, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their qualities and degrees; as at length is ſpecified in theſe Acts. And it being declared by the fifth Act of the firſt Seſſion of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> late Parliament, That it is His <hi>Majesties</hi> Prerogative-Royal and undoubted Right, to have the power of raiſing in Armes the Subjects of this Kingdom, and of the commanding, ordering and disbanding, or otherwayes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing thereof as He ſhall think fit. As alſo, the Eſtates of Parliament of this Kingdom, in recogniſance of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royal Prerogative foreſaid, and in a further acknowledgement of their duty, Having, by the twenty fifth Act of the laſt Seſſion of the foreſaid Parliament, made offer to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> of twenty thouſand Footmen and two thouſand Horſemen, ſufficiently armed and furniſhed with fourty dayes proviſion, to be raiſed from the ſeveral Shires of the Kingdom, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion expreſt in that Act, to be in readineſs as they ſhall be called for by His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to march to any part of His Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Scotland, England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> for any ſervice wherein His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Honour, Authority or Greatneſs may be concerned. And His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> finding it expedient that the foreſaid number of Foot and Horſe ſhould be modelled and trained in military diſcipline, to the effect they might be in greater readineſs and fitneſs for His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Service when they ſhould be called for, Having, by advice of His Privy Council, conſtituted and ſettled a Militia of Horſe and Foot in many Shires of the Kingdom, according to the proportions mentioned in the foreſaid Act; and in ſome other Shires a Militia of Horſe only; having thought fit in this exigent, for important reaſons, to change their Foot into a proportion of Horſe, ſuteable to the charge of their propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Foot: And having nominated and appointed the Collonels and Lieutenant-Collonels of Foot, and Captains of Horſe; And the Lords of Prvy Council having, by His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Order and Warrand, appointed Commiſſioners of the Militia in the ſeveral Shires, ordered the election of the inferiours Officers, appointed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33954:4"/>particular dayes of Rendezvous, the way of liſting of Foot-ſouldiers, ordered fit allowances to be given to the Foot and Horſemen every day of the Rendezvous; That Collours, Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darts, Drums and Trumpets be provided at the charge of the Shire; and having given ſeveral other Orders and Inſtructions concerning the ordering and diſpoſing of the Militia, The Eſtates of Parliament do in all duty acknowledge His <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſingular Wiſdom and tender Care of this His ancient Kingdom, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting and ſettling the foreſaid Militia. Likeas, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of His Eſtates of Parliament, doth Ratifie and Approve the conſtitution and model of the Militia, as the ſame is eſtabliſhed by His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice of His Privy Council: And particularly, their appointing dayes for Rendezvous, ordering fit allowances to be given to the Foot and Horſemen the ſaids dayes of their Rendezvous; And all Acts, Commiſſions, Orders and Inſtructiones paſt and emitted by the Council concerning the Militia, and their whole proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings relating thereto. And Statutes and Ordaines, that in all time coming there be allowed to each Footman ſix ſhillings <hi>Scots,</hi> and to each Horſeman eighteen ſhillings <hi>Scots,</hi> every day of the Rendezvous, to be payed be the Heretors; And that the ſaid ſix ſhillings to be payed to the Footmen, be refounded to the Heretors by the men-tennents and ſervants for whom the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are put out, and who are not liſted in the Militia. And alſo Statutes and Ordaines, that the Rendezvous be punctually keeped, that Horſe and Foot be duely outreiked and ſufficiently armed, that Fractions with their proportions of the price of the Collours, Drums, Standarts, and Trumpets be timeouſly payed Likeas, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> with advice foreſaid, doth give power and warrand to the Commiſſioners of the Militia in the reſpective Shires, to fine parties for the Souldiers abſence from the Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deizvous, not exceeding ſix pounds <hi>Scots</hi> for the Horſemen, and two pounds <hi>Scots</hi> for the Footman abſent ilk day of the Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous; And likewiſe, ſuch as ſhall be deficient in the outreik of Horſe or Foot, or in payment of the fractions thereof, or of the proportions of Collours, Drums, Standart, and Trumpets, or of the pay allowed by this preſent Act to the Horſemen or Footmen, the men-tennents and ſervants for whom the Foot-men are put out, being alwayes lyable to relieve the reſpective Heretors of the payment of the fines aforeſaid, inſo far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the deficiency in outreik of Foot, or payment of the fractions thereof, or abſents of the Footmen from the dayes of Rendezvous. And to the effect, more ready obedienuc may be given to this preſent Act and Ordinance, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice foreſaid (without derogation from any power already given by the Inſtructions or Acts of Council) doth authorize and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power the Commiſſioners of the Militia in the reſpective Shires,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33954:4"/>or any three of them (two of the <hi>quorum</hi> not being Officers) alter tryal taken that parties have been abſent from the Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous, or deficient in the outreiks and payments foreſaid; to give order and warrand to any one of the Serjants of Foot of the reſpective Companies, or Corporals of Horſe to be named by the ſaids Commiſſioners, to poind and diſtreinzie the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ieſt Goods and Geer of theſe abſent or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ficient, wherever the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me may be found, appriſe and make ſale thereof towards the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſums ſpecified in the ſaid Warrand, and of the charges and expenſes of the poinding and appriſing; theſe charges alwayes not exceeding als much more as the ſums for which the poinding ſhall be uſed. Likeas, His <hi>Majeſly,</hi> with advice foreſaid, conſtitutes the ſaid perſon, to whom the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Order ſhall be directed, Sheriff in that part; with power to him, by vertue of that Order, to poind the Goods without ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of carrying the ſame to the Paroch church or Mercat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſs of the head Burgh of the Shire to be appriſed; and to do and act in the excution of the ſaid Order, ſicklike as a Meſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at Armes may do by the Law, in execution of Letters of poinding and appriſing given under His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Signet: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding alwayes, that the goods poinded be valued and appr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by two honeſt ſworn men, whoſe oathes the ſaid Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riff in that part is authorized to take to that effect; And declares, That it ſhall be leiſome to the party from whom the Goods ſhall be poinded, to redeem the ſame within ſix dayes after the poind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by payment of the ſums, for which the poinding ſhall be uſed, expenſes of the poinding foreſaid, and twelve ſhillings ſcots each day during the not redemption. And in caſe the party do not redeem the goods poinped within the ſpace foreſaid, declares that it ſhall be lawfull to the ſaid Sheriff in that part to retain the goods or ſell the ſame, with deduction of the third of the ſum to which they were appriſed, He alwayes being countable for the price thereof to the Commiſſioners of the Militia, who are to ſee the party, from whom the Goods were poinded, ſatisfied of the <hi>ſuperplus</hi> of the price if any be of the Goods for which the poinding was uſed, expenſes foreſaid of the poinding, third part of the value to which the Goods were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, with twelve ſhilling <hi>Scots</hi> ilk day during the ſpace that the party had power to redeem, being alwayes deduced, and declares the ſaid Warrand, being ſigned by three of the ſaids Commiſſioners (one of them only being an officer) to have the force and ſtrength of an Decreet; and that there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of any Precept or Charge to follow thereon: And that the poinding and appriſing ſo uſed, by vertue of the ſaid War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, is and ſhall be als lawfull and valid, as if all the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities requiſite and uſual in poindings were obſerved; whereanent His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, doth diſpenſe in this caſe of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33954:5"/>the Militia. And it is declared, that theſe who are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently armed or mounted at the Rendezvous, ſhall be holden as abſent therefrom, and ſhall be fined and poinded accordingly in manner foreſaid. And for preveening debates that may ariſe the time of muſtering, it is Declared, that Lieutenants and Cornets of Horſe ſhall be reckoned of the number of Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, appointed to be put out in the reſpective Shires: But prejudice alwayes to any of the ſaids Officers, to claim and ſute payment of Fractions, if they be Leaders of Horſe. As alſo, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, doth authorize and impower the Lords of His Privy Council from time to time, to appoint dayes of Rendezvous, and to give ſuch further or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as ſhall be requiſite for the full eſtabliſhmen of the Militia in every particular thereof; and to call for an account from the ſeveral Shires of their procecure and diligence in ſettling the ſame. And commands and requires all His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects of whatſoever degree or quality, to give due and ready obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to all ſuch orders and directions as they ſhall receive from His <hi>Majſties</hi> Privy Council, relating to the Militia, under the pains and certification contained in any Acts made, or to be made by them thereanent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33954:5"/>
               <head>III. <hi>ACT for regiſtration of Inſtruments of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation</hi> ad remanentiam.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>November</hi> 16. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Saveraign Lord, with the advice of the Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and Ordains, That all Inſtruments of Reſignation that ſhall be made in the Superiour hands, <hi>ad remanen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> (fourty dayes after the publication here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) be regiſtrate within threeſcore dayes after the date thereof, in the ſame manner and way and at the ſame rates as Renunciations, Seiſings or Reverſions: To the effect, the Lieges may the better know, that the Infeft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which was granted to the Reſigners is thereby void and extinct, and that they may be put <hi>in mala fide</hi> to contract with the Reſigner thereanent, or to compriſe the ſame from him, otherwayes the ſaid Reſignation to be null. It is alwayes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Declared, That the Inſtruments of Reſignation of Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Lands and Fiſhings holden in free Burgage, being regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in the Town Court Books of the Burgh, ſhall not fall within the certification of this preſent Act.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>IV. <hi>ACT concerning poinding before the dayes of the Charge expire.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>November</hi> 16. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord, with advice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, that hereafter it ſhall not be lawful to poind moveables upon regiſtrate Bonds, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creets for perſonal Debts, while the parties be firſt Charged, and the dayes of the Charge be expired: With certification, that poinding otherwayes uſed ſhall be null, and the poinders ſhall be puniſhed and proceeded againſt as ſpuiliers; But prejudice alwayes of any Decreets re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered at the inſtance of Heretors againſt their Tennents in their own Courts; whereupon it ſhall be lawful to them to uſe poind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as formerly; And but prejudice to Superiours to uſe poinding againſt their Vaſſals for their Few-duties, as they might lawfully have done of before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33954:6"/>
               <head>V. <hi>ACT for the ſecurity of the Perſons of Miniſters.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>November</hi> 30. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the Kings <hi>Majeſty,</hi> conſidering how juſt and neceſſar it was, that the Orthodox Clergy ſhould be protected from the violence of diſaffected and diſloyal perſons; Did therefore, with advice of His Privy Council, by His Royal Proclamations of the fifteenth of <hi>March</hi> and thirteenth of <hi>June,</hi> one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty ſeven, command and charge all Heretors, Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renters and others, having any real Intereſt or Rent within the ſeveral Paroches of the Kingdom, to protect, defend and ſecure the Perſons, Families and Goods of their Miniſters, not only in the exerciſe of the Miniſterial Function, but in their dwelling Houſes; or being elſewhere within the Paroch, from all injuries, affronts and prejudices which they might incur in their Perſons or Goods, from the violence and invaſion of any diſaffected, diſloyal or other wicked perſon: With certification, if the actors of ſuch outrages ſhould not be apprehended and brought to tryal, by the means and diligence of the Parochioners, the Parochioners ſhould be decerned to pay to ſuffering Miniſters for reparation, damage and intereſt, ſuch a ſum and fine as His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Council ſhould determine; as is more fully expreſt in the ſaids Proclamations. And the Eſtates of Parliament, having taken to their conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the proceedings of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Council herein; and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the protection of the Orthodox Clergy, and the reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the inſolency of diſaffected, diſloyal and wicked perſons at this time, did require more nor ordinary means and care from His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Council; Have therefore thought fit, Likeas, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of His Eſtates, doth hereby Ratifie and Approve the two Proclamations aforeſaid, and the proceedings of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Council in proſecution thereof; and authorizeth them ſtill to proſecute the ſame as occaſion ſhal offer, until His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in His next Parliament give farther Orders therein. And it is Declared, that this Act is and ſhall be but prejudice of any former Laws and Acts of Parliament made againſt the invaders of Miniſters, and of the pains therein contained; And particularly the twenty ſeventh Act of the eleventh Parliament of King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth, and ſeventh Act of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt His Parliament in <hi>Anno,</hi> 1633. Which Acts His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, doth hereby Ratifie and Approve,, and Declares the ſame to ſtand in full force, ſtrength and effect in time coming.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="act">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33954:6"/>
               <head>VI. <hi>ACT. for the ordering of Suſpenſions of the Benefices and Stipends of the Clergy.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>November</hi> 30. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kings <hi>Majeſty</hi> being careful that the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance of the Clergy be duely ſecured un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and that they be not withdrawn by unneceſſar Law-ſutes for recovery there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; Doth therefore, with advice and conſent of His Eſtates of Parliament, Statute and Ordain That no Supenſion ſhall be paſt in time coming againſt any Archbiſhop, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Miniſter of the Goſpel or Univerſities and Colledges, of any Charges to be given at their inſtances for payment of the Rents of their Benefices, Stipends or Colledge-rents, where they have ſpecial Decreets againſt the Heretors or poſſeſſors due and lyable in payment thereof to them, except upon production of Diſcharges or conſignation of the ſums charged for, if the Rent of the Benefice or Stipend conſiſt in money; or of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred merks Scots for ilk Chalder of Victual where the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in Victual, and proportionally if the Victual charged for be leſs then a Chalder, without prejudice to the Lords of Seſſion to modifie a greater or leſs ſum for the Chalder of Victual, as they ſhall find cauſe at the diſcuſſing of the Suſpenſion. And if any Bill of Suſpenſion of a general Charge ſhal be preſented in time of Seſſion, That the ordinary Lord upon the Bills, before the paſſing thereof, call for the Chargers at the Bar, that they may inſtruct the ground of the Charge: And in caſe it ſhall be found by the Lords of the Seſſion, at the diſcuſſing of the Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that either the Charge hath been malitiouſly given or mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly ſuſpended, That the Lords modifie a fifth part of the ſum charged for, of expenſes of Plea to be payed by the malitious Charger or Suſpender.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="act">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33954:7"/>
               <head>VII. <hi>ACT for Naturalization of Strangers.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 8. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord, out of His Innate Bounty and Royal Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to favour and protect Strangers, and for the encreaſe and promoving of Trade and Manufactories, being garciouſly pleaſed and willing to give encouragement to Strangers to repair to, and dwell and reſide within this Kingdom; Hath therefore thought fit; Likeas, His <hi>Majeſties</hi> with advice and conſent of His Eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doth hereby Statute, Ordain and Declare, That all Strangers, being of the Proteſtant Religion, either ſuch who having Eſtates ſhall think fit to bring the ſame to this Kingdom, to dwell and inhabite within the ſame; or who ſhall come to ſet up new Works and Manufactories therein, and ſhall repair to, and ſettle their abode, dwelling and reſidence within this Kingdom; ſhall be, and are hereby naturalized as native born Subjects of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and are to enjoy His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> Royal Protection, the benefit of the Law, and all other Priviledges which a Native doth enjoy, als freely in all reſpects, as if they themſelves had been born within the ſame; and that they ſhall have liberty and freedom of Trade, and freedom to buy and purchaſe Lands, Heretages, and other Goods move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and immoveable, and to enjoy the ſame by ſucceſſion, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe or donation, or any other way; and to diſpoſe thereof and tranſmit them to their Heirs and Succeſſors, who are to ſucceed thereunto: And to enjoy all other Liberties, Priviledges and Capacities which do belong to, and are competent, or may and ſhall belong to any native Subject born within this Kingdom. And further, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> doth Declare, that upon applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be made unto Him by theſe Strangers, He will grant unto them the free and publick exerciſe of their Religion in their own Languages, and the liberty of having Churches
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33954:7"/>within this His Kingdom. It is alwayes hereby provided, that no perſon or perſons ſhall have the benefit of this act, until firſt by Petition to the Lords of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Privy Council, containing an exact deſignation of their names, places of their birth and former reſidence, and that they are of the Proteſtant Religion, it be found by the Council, that they are qualified according to this Act, and ought to have the benefit thereof. And it is hereby Declared, that theſe preſents, with an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of the Act of Council, in favours of the ſaids perſons to the effect aforeſaid, ſhall be unto them a ſufficient Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation to all intents and purpoſes. Which Extract ſhall be given to them freely, without payment of any money or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; ſave only the Fee of nine pounds <hi>Scots</hi> money to the Clerks of Council and their Servants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="act">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:33954:8"/>
               <head>VIII. <hi>ACT concerning the Bullion.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 8. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord conſidering, that by divers former Acts of Parliament made by the Kings <hi>Majeſty</hi> and His Royal Anceſtors, and ſpecially by the thirty ſeventh Act of the firſt Seſſion of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> firſt Parliament, it is Statute and Ordained, that all and whatſover Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties yearly exported forth of this Kingdom, ſhould be lyable to the payment of Bullion, twelve denier fine, according to the quantities contained in the Alphabet of Bullion thereto adjoyned, and that for the yearly ſupport of a ſtock of Coinage within the Kingdom, and for ſupplying of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Mint, being a part of His Prerogative Royal. And His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the Eſtates of Parliament, being ſtill willing to ſupport and encourage the ſame, and to provide for all neceſſary wayes and remedies for increaſing the ſtock of Coinage within the Kingdom, and eſpecially thoſe that may be of moſt advantage, and may moſt encourage the Manufactories and the natural growth and native Commodities of the Kingdom; And finding, that the removing of the Bullion from the whole native Commodities and others exported forth of this Kingdom, and that the impoſing of the ſaid Bullion upon the Commodities imported, or ſome conſiderable part thereof, may very much contribute thereto; And being reſolved, that His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Mint ſhould be hereby encouraged, and that no hurt or derogation ſhould thereto occur by this change. Therefore, His <hi>Majesty,</hi> with advice and conſent of His Eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Declares, That all and whatſover native Commodities of this Kingdom, and others that ſhall be exported forth thereof, contained in the foreſaid Alphabet of Bullion, after the ſecond day of <hi>February</hi> next to come, one thouſand ſix hundred and ſeventy years, ſhall be free, and are hereby diſcharged of the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all quantities of Bullion therein contained: And the Cuſtomers and their Deputies are hereby prohibited and diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take ſurety or pledges, or to uſe any other exaction upon the Merchants therefore, under all higheſt pain. And His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, Reſcinds and Annulls any Cauſes contained in the foreſaid thirty ſeventh Act of the firſt Seſſion of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> firſt Parliament, or in any other Acts of Parliament, in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33954:8"/>ſo far allanerly as the ſame impoſes Bullion upon the native Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of this Kingdom, and others to be exported forth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and no further: And in lieu and place thereof, Statutes and Ordains, That the imported Goods and Commodities under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written be lyable in payment of theſeveral quantities of Bullion aftermentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> Spaniſh, Rheniſh and Brandy-wines of all ſorts, each Tun twenty four ounces, twelve denier fine; French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wines of all ſorts, every Tun twelve ounces; Loaf-ſuggar the hundred weight, ſix ounces; Playing-cards, one ounce the groſs; Paper for Printing and Writing of all ſorts, one ounce every ſix rimms; Gray-paper, every twelve rimms one ounce; Deals every thouſand five ounces; Single-trees, every thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand five ounces; Double-trees, every thouſand ten ounces; Double-double-trees, and all other greater Fir-timber, every thouſand twenty ounces; Steel, every hundred weight one ounce; Iron and Iron-work beaten of all ſorts, every Tun two ounces; Onions and Aples, every two Barrals one ounce; Mum-beer, every Barral four ounces; Prunes, every Tun four ounces; Raiſins, Currants and Figs, every Tun ten ounces; Iron-pots of all ſorts, every dozen one ounce; Soap, every Barrel two ounces, Suggar-candy, every hundred weight ten ounces; Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-kettles, Braſs-pans, and all other made work in Braſs or Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Yetline or beaten, every hundred weight four ounces; Mader, every thouſand weight five ounces; Hats of all ſorts, every three dozen two ounces; Window-glaſs of all ſorts, every Cheſt one ounce; Limons and Oranges, each thouſand one ounce; Hops of all ſorts, every hundred weight one ounce; Spaniſh-leather, Marikin, Tanned-leather, Wild-leather, and all other ſorts of leather, except <hi>Muſcovia</hi>-leather, every hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred weight one ounce; Gloves of all ſorts, each dozen one ounce, Whale-bane or Baline, ilk two hundred weight one ounce. And Statutes and Ordains, that the Merchant or other importers of the abovewritten Commodities or any of them, make ready payment of the foreſaids quantities of Bullion hereby impoſed, to the Officers of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Mint for the time, being of the fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of twelve Deniers, and being baſer to be conſidered by weight and reckoning, and that immediately upon the entry of the ſaids Goods; And in caſe the ſaid importer ſhall fail to pay in the ſaids Bullion at his entry, he ſhall be holden and aſtricted, to make payment of the ſum of twelve Shillings <hi>Scots</hi> for ilk ounce thereof to the Collectors, at the Port or Precinct where he enters the ſaids Goods; and which money ſo payed by him at his entry, ſhall be redeemable from the ſaids Collectors, upon the payment of the foreſaids quantities of Bullion in to the Officers of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Mint: Provided alwayes, ſuch payment of Bullion be made within fourty dayes, after the date of the entry of the Goods, and not thereafter. And it is hereby Declared, That it ſhall not be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33954:9"/>lawful to the ſaids Tackſ-men, Collectors or their Deputies, to permit the ſaids importers to break Bulk, or to give them Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ire's or other warrant thereanent, till firſt the ſaids Importers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port or produce the Mint-maſters receipt of the due quantity or Bullion payed <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> or elſe, that the Tackſ-men Collectors or their Deputies, receive payment of twelve Shillings <hi>Scots</hi> for ilk ounce of Bullion not delivered in to the Mint; and for ilk ounce of Bullion of twelve Denier fine, ſopayed in to the Mint <hi>in ſpecie</hi> by the Importer, he is to have delivered back to him in His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Coin three pounds ten pennies <hi>Scots,</hi> and for ilk ounce of eleven Deniers fine, he is to have delivered back to him fifty five ſhillings nine pennies <hi>Scots,</hi> and ſo proportionably conform to the fineneſs of the Bullion given in, and that in ſatisfaction of all Dues whatſover that can be acclaimed by the Officers of the Mint, for His <hi>Majeſty</hi> or otherwayes. And whereas, by the former Acts of Parliament made anent Bullion, the general Tackſ-men and Collectors of the Cuſtoms and their Deputies, were bound and oblieged to take ſicker Surety or Pledges, ſuch as they would be anſwerable for, for the Bullion to be brought in and which then lay upon export, and that what reſted not delivered to the Mint, the ſaids Tackſ-men, Collectors and their Deputies, were to be anſwerable therefore; And that by the conſtant practice of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Exchequer, the ſaids Tackſ-men and Collectors, by their Tacks and Commiſſions given to them, and Obligations granted by them, are bound to make count, reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and payment of the whole Bullion then ariſing upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of this Kingdom, And leſt His <hi>Majeſty</hi> or his ſaid Mint ſhould ſuſtain any hurt or prejudice, or be at any uncertainty by looſing of thoſe bonds, or by this change; Therefore it is hereby Statute and Ordained that all general Tackſ-men of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Cuſtoms of this Kingdom, general Collectors of the ſame and their Deputies preſent and to come, ſhall be, and are hereby bound and oblieged, <hi>virtute Officii,</hi> and by the acceptation of their Tack or Office, to make count, reckoning and payment to the Officers of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Mint, of all and whatſoever quantities of Bullion that ſhall yearly ariſe upon the imported Commodities aforementioned, and which ſhall be delivered by the Merchant <hi>in ſpecie;</hi> and alſo to make payment of all ſuch ſums of Money, as ſhall be payed by the Merchant to them, in place of Bullion, at the aforeſaid rate of twelve ſhillings <hi>per ounce,</hi> to the General and Maſter of the Mint for the time being, and that quarterly; beginning the firſt quarters payment at the terme of <hi>Whitſonday</hi> next, one thouſand fix hundred and ſeventy and ſo-forth yearly and quarterly thereafter. And whereas, the ſaids Tackſ-men, Collectors or their Deputies, were formerly holden and aſtricted to give in exact accounts of the whole Commodities exported yearly forth of this Kingdom upon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33954:9"/>Oath, wherby the full charge of the Bullion was yearly known; And to the effect, that the full charge of the bullion now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon the foreſids Commodities imported, may be als ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known: It is hereby Statute and Ordained, That the ſaids Tackſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Collectors or their Deputies at all the Ports or Precincts within this Kingdom, ſhall givein yearly in Exchequer the exact account of the ſeveral quantities of the Commodities, whereupon Bullion is hereby impoſed, and that upon Oath, at the feaſt and terme of <hi>Martimas</hi> yearly: As alſo, to exhibite and produce the ſubſcribed Entries by the Marchants of the foreſaids Goods imported; and for that effect, that Letters of Horning be directed againſt the ſaid ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Collectors, Tackſmen and their Deputies, by the Lords of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Exchequer, upon a charge of ſix dayes: And it is hereby declared, That the ſaids Tackſ-men, Collectors or their Deputies ſhall be holden and aſtricted to deliver to the importer, Certificates of the forſaid Bullion <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> or of the Money payed therefore at the rate foreſaid, <hi>gratis.</hi> And whereas by the meaning of this Act, it is left in the option of the importer, either to pay Bullion <hi>in ſpecie</hi> or to pay money for the ſame, at the rate oftwelve Shillings <hi>per ounce,</hi> and that the Money ſo payed is to be delivered to the General and Maſter of the Mint, by the ſaids Tackſ-men Collectors and their Deputies, and thereby the ſaid General and Maſter are oblieged to import the ſtock of Bullion them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Therefore it is hereby Statute and Ordained, that the ſaids Officers ſhall be oblieged to Coin the ſaid Bullion ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by them, and to make the ſame paſs His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Irons, and that the ſaids Officers be controled by their Letters of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the ſaids ſums of Money granted by them, to the ſaids Tackſ-men, Collectors and their Deputies. And it is hereby Declared, That the foreſaids whole Commodities imported after the foreſaid day, ſhall be liable to the ſeveral proportions of Bullion above ſpecified, notwithſtanding of any Act or Acts of Parliament formerly made, or to be made in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in favours of any Manufactories, Companies of Fiſhing or Trade, or other Acts whatſoever, which are hereby Declared not to impede the payment of Bullion impoſed upon the import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Goods foreſaids, in manner abovementioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="act">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33954:12"/>
               <head>IX <hi>ACT concerning Preſcriptions.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 8. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord, with advice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and Ordains, That all Arreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be uſed hereafter upon De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creets, regiſtrate Bonds, Diſpoſitions or Contracts, not purſued and inſiſted on within five years after the laying on thereof, ſhall after that time preſcrive, And that all Arreſtments already uſed upon the ground aforeſaid, ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerive within five years after the date hereof. And that all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtments, uſed or to be uſed upon dependance of Actions, ſhall likewayes preſcrive within five years after Sentence is obtained in the ſaids Actions, if the ſaids Arreſtments be not purſued or inſiſted on within that time, And likewayes, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, Statutes and Ordains, That Miniſters Stipends and Multars not purſued for within five years after the ſame are due, And likewayes Mails and Duties of Tennents, not being purſued within five years after the Tennents ſhall remove from the Lands for which the Mails and duties are craved, ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerive in all time coming: Except the ſaids Miniſters Stipends, Multars, Mails and Duties ſhall be offered to be proven to be due and reſting owing, by the defenders their Oaths, or by a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial writ under their hands acknowledgeing what is reſting owing; And that all Bargains concerning moveables or ſums of money, probable by Witneſſes, ſhall only be probable by Writ or Oath of Party, if the ſame be not purſued for within five years after the making of the Bargain. And further, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> withadvice and conſent foreſaid, Statutes and Ordains, That all Actions proceeding upon Warnings, Spuilȝies, Ejections, Arreſtments, or for Miniſters Stipends and others foreſaid, ſhall preſcrive within ten years, except the ſaid Action be wakened every five years: But prejudice alwayes of any of the ſaids Actions, which by former Acts of Parliament are appointed to preſcrive in a ſhorter time. And alſo Statutes and Ordains, That Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lograph miſſive Letters, and Holograph Bonds, and Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Compt-books without Witneſſes, not being purſued
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33954:10"/>for within twenty years, ſhall preſcrive in all time thereafter; Except the purſuer offer to prove, by the defenders Oath, the verity of the ſaids Holograph Bonds and Letters, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions in the Compt-books. It is alwayes hereby De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, That Preſcriptions ſhall not run in any of the Caſes foreſaid, againſt Minors during the years of their Minority.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="act">
               <head>X. <hi>ACT concerning Interruptions.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 8. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord with advice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and Ordains, that all Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, as to the Rights of Lands be citations, ſhall in all time hereafter be execute by Meſſengers at Arms, and againſt the defenders perſonally or at their dwelling places, and at the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roch Churches in the time of Divine Service, or immediately after; And in caſe the Parties be forth of the Kingdom, at the Mercat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſs of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and Peer and Shore of <hi>Lieth,</hi> upon three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore dayes. And that all Citations that ſhall be made uſe of for Interruptions, whether in real or perſonal Rights, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed every ſeven years, otherwayes to preſcrive; Except the Parties be Minors: In which caſe this Act is not to be extended againſt them, during the years of their Minority.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="act">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:33954:11"/>
               <head>XI. <hi>ACT concerning the forfeiture of perſons in the late Rebellion.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 15. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord and His Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, having conſidered the Proceſs of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, purſued and deduced at the inſtance of Sir <hi>John Nisbet</hi> of <hi>Dirletoun,</hi> His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat, by Warrand and Order of His <hi>Majesties</hi> Privy Council before the Juſtice, againſt the perſons after mentioned, for their treaſonable riſing in Armes, and being in, and having acceſſion to, the late Rebellion in the Weſtern Shires, in the year of our Lord, one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty ſix; with the Libels, Interloquiturs, Probations, Depoſitions of Witneſſes, and the verdicts of Inqueſts and dooms of Forfeitures proceeding their upon: Do find, that the Juſtice and their Aſſeſſors appointed by the Council in the ſaid Proceſs, in finding the ſaid Libels to be relevant, and admitting the ſame to the knowledge of Inqueſts; and the foreſaid Inqueſts in finding the ſame to be verified and proven, and in giving their verdicts and dooms of Forfeiture theirupon <hi>reſpectivé;</hi> Have proceeded juſtly and warrantably upon relevant Libels, and clear evidences and probation; And therefore, do Ratifie and Approve their Proceedings, Interloquiturs, Verdicts and reſpective Dooms and Sentences of Forfeiture given and pronounced by them in the ſaid Proceſs, <hi>viz.</hi> The Sentence and Doom of Forfeiture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt Collonel <hi>James Wallace, Joſeph Lermonth, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Mckclellan</hi> of <hi>Barſcobe,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Welch,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Smith, Patrick Liſtoun</hi> in <hi>Calder, William Liſtoun</hi> his ſon, <hi>William Porterfield</hi> of <hi>Quarreltoun</hi> pronounced upon the fifteenth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the year of God, one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty ſeven years; And the other Sentence and Doom of Forfeiture pronounced againſt <hi>William Muir</hi> of <hi>Caldwell, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Caldwell,</hi> eldeſt Son to the Good-man of <hi>Caldwell, Robert Ker</hi> of <hi>Kerſland,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Cunninghame</hi> of <hi>Bedland, Alexander Porterfield,</hi> Brother to <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reltoun, John Maxwel</hi> of <hi>Monreith</hi> younger, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mckclellan</hi> of <hi>Belmagahan,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gabriel Semple,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Crookſhanks, Patrick Mcknaught</hi> in <hi>Cumnock,</hi> upon the ſixteenth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33954:11"/>ſaid year of God, one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty ſeven years? And Decerns and Ordains the ſaids Proceſs and Dooms and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Forfeiture foreſaid, to be valid and effectual to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes, notwithſtanding that the ſaids perſons found guilty and convicted of the crimes foreſaid, did not compear in the ſaids Proceſs; And Declares, that the ſaid Sentence and Dooms of Forfeiture ſhall be of als great force and ſtrength, as if the ſaids p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſons had compeared, or the ſame had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in Parliament. And His <hi>Majeſty</hi> with conſent foreſaid, doth Approve His ſaid Advocats ſervice in the ſaid affair. And in reſpect it were againſt reaſon and juſtice, that when any perſon or pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſons are accuſed of high Treaſon, for riſing in Armes againſt His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> or His Authority, when they are cited to underly the Law before the Juſtice, if they do not appear, that their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and contumacy, which ought to be an aggravation, if any can be, of ſo high and horrid a crime, ſhould be of any advantage to them: Therefore, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, doth Statute and Ordain, that in time coming in all ſuch caſes of treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able riſing in Armes, and open and manifeſt Rebellion againſt His <hi>Majeſty</hi> or His Succeſſors and their Authority, His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat for the time, may and ought to inſiſt againſt, and proſecute ſuch perſons as he ſhall be ordered by His <hi>Majeſty</hi> or His Privy Council to purſue: And if they be cited and do not appear, the Juſtice notwithſtanding of their abſence, may and ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to conſider, and give their Interloquiturs upon the Libel; and if it be ſound relevant, to admit the ſame to the knowledge of an Aſſize, and upon the verdict of the Inqueſt, finding the ſame to be proven, the Doom and Sentence of Forfeiture ought to proceed, and be given and pronounced in the ſame manner, as if the perſons accuſed had compeared and were preſent. And His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, doth remit to the Juſtice General, Juſtice-Clerk or Juſtice-Deputes, the Summons and Proceſs of Treaſon, intended at the inſtance of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Advocat, againiſt certain perſons therein mentioned, for their acceſſion to the ſaid Rebellion, and depending before His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the Eſtates: With power to them to proceed, notwithſtanding of the abſence of the ſaids perſons; And if the ſaids Summones be found relevant and proven by the verdict of Inqueſt, to pronounce the Sentence and Doom of Forfeiture thereupon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="act">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:33954:12"/>
               <head>XII. <hi>ACT concerning the Exciſe and Cuſtomes.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 15. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as many debates, queſtions and inextri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable difficulties do and may ariſe, in levying and inbringing of the Exciſe, impoſed by the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Act of the firſt Seſſion of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> firſt Parliament, to the great prejudice of His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and of the Trade of this Kingdom: Therefore, and for preventing and clearing of the ſame, and to the effect, the ſaid Exciſe may be more orderly and eaſily levyed and collected, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of His Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and Orda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, That notwithſtanding the ſaid Exciſe is due and payable by the Retailers, yet the Importers ſhall be layable for the ſame in time coming, at the rates contained in the ſaid Act, for Wines of all ſorts, Vinegar and Salt, as they are particularly expreſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and that under the proviſions after-ſpecified: To wit, that what ſhall not be payed by the Retailers, ſhall be compleatly made up by the Importers, within twelve Moneths after the importation thereof, for which they are to give ſufficient ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the Farmers or Collectors of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Exciſe, at the entry of the ſaids Wines, which are to be according as they ſhall be loaded at the Port from whence they came; And for the ſaid Importers, their greater caſe and encouragement, His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, doth Statute and Ordain, that the Collectors or Farmers of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Exciſe in all time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhall grant abatement to the ſaid Importers of the fourth part of the ſaid Exciſe duties of all Wines and Vinegar import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and entred by them, in conſideration and upon the account of leckage and decayed Wines, and other hazards and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies. And further, It is Statute and Ordained, for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and greater eaſe and advantage of Trade and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, that the Importers of all other Goods and Commodities, except what is excepted from the duties of Exciſe by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Act of Parliament, ſhall pay the Exciſe thereof, according to the Books of Rates for His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Cuſtoms, and as the ſaids Commodities are and ſhall be valued and rated in the ſame; And if any of the ſaids Commodities be not contained in the Books of Rates, the Exciſe of the ſame is declared to be five <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33954:10"/>according to the value of the ſaid Goods; And the Exciſe of the ſaid Commodities is to be payed at the entring of the ſame in the Exciſe-office, unleſs the ſaid Exciſe-duty exceed the ſum of one hundred Marks <hi>Scots;</hi> in which caſe, the ſaid Importers ſhall be obliedged to give ſufficient ſecurity for payment of the ſaid Exciſe-duty, within ſix Moneths after the entring of the ſame; they making it alwayes evident, that no Merchant ſhall make entry of any Goods, but what properly belongs to himſelf. And for further encouragment of Trade and Traffick, It is Statute and Ordained, that all Goods and Merchandiſe whatſoever im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and which ſhall be inſtructed to be really exported, within twelve Moneths after the entring thereof, ſhal be free of Exciſe; and in caſe of payment thereof, the ſame ſhall be repayed at the exportation of the ſaid Commodities, the Importers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes making faith, that the Commodities exported, are the ſame which were imported and entred; and in caſe bond of ſecurity hath been given for the Exciſe of the ſaid Commodities, the ſame ſhall be returned unregiſtrat, or diſcharged if the ſame be regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat. And for the regulating of the Exciſe of Salt, and the better levying and inbringing of the ſame, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent foreſaid, Statutes and Ordains, that the Importers of forraign Salt of all ſorts, at their entring of the ſame at the Exciſe-office, ſhall give ſufficient ſecurity for payment of the Exciſe thereof conform to the Rates contained in the foreſaid fourteenth Act, and that the Importers ſhall be oblieged by the ſaid ſecurity, to pay the ſaids reſpective Exciſe-duties, for ſuch parcels of the ſaid Salt as ſhall be ratailed, when and as the ſame ſhall happen to be retailed, and to pay compleatly the whole Exciſe of the ſaid Salt, within twelve Moneths after the entring thereof, and that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſaid Salt hath been expended and imployed upon the cureing of Fiſhes or not; Providing alwayes, their be abated and allowed to them, the Exciſe of all Salt that ſhall happen to be caſt away at Sea; And likewiſe, the Exciſe of Salt expended upon Fiſhes, that may happen to be caſt away betwixt one Port and another, before the ſame be entred, to be exported out of this Kingdom, the wrak and quantities of the Salt or Fiſhes loſt thereby, being alwayes ſufficiently inſtructed. And further, it is Ordained, that all In-land Salt conſumed within this Kingdom, whether the ſame be expended upon Fiſhes or imployed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſhall be lyable to the duty of Exciſe, expreſt in the ſaid Act, which ſhall be payed by the firſt buyer thereof, and that before it be carried from the Salt-pans where it is bought; And albeit it be provided in manner foreſaid, that the Exciſe-duties <hi>reſpective</hi> above-mentioned, ſhould be payed for Forraign and In-land Salt, whether the ſame be imployed upon Fiſhes or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and that in reſpect of the great difficulties, to clear and make appear what Salt is imployed upon Fiſhes or not, and that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33954:13"/>His <hi>Majeſty</hi> may be prejudged of the Exciſe of Salt, upon ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pretences, that the ſame hath been, or is to be imployed upon Fiſhes; Yet, nevertheleſs, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> being moſt willing to give all due encouragement to the Trade of Fiſhing, and that whatſoever Salt ſhall be imployed and expended in order to the ſaid Trade, and upon the cureing of Fiſhes to be exported, ſhall in effect be free of Exciſe; and upon, and after mature and exact conſideration of the quantity of Sait, neceſſary and ſufficient for each Laſt of Herring and White-fiſh of any kind, and of each Laſt of Salmond, and what the Exciſe of the ſame Salt <hi>reſpectivé</hi> will amount to, finding that the Exciſe of the Salt of the Laſt of Herring and White-fiſh, will amount to the ſum of ten pounds four ſhillings <hi>Scots,</hi> and that the Exciſe of the Salt of each Laſt of Salmond, will amount to the ſum of twelve pounds, money foreſaid. His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, Statutes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, that there ſhall be no Cuſtom exacted at the exportation of the ſaids Herring and White-fiſh, and that whatever the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ten pounds four ſhillings of Exciſe, ſhall exceed the Cuſtom payable for the ſaids Herring and White-fiſh, at the exportation thereof, ſhall be duly and timeouſly payed to the Merchant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters, without any delay, reward or abatement for each Laſt of Herring and White-fiſh of any kind whatſoever that ſhall be exported out of this Kingdom: And that the foreſaid ſum of twelve pounds, for the Exciſe of the Salt of each Laſt of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, at the entry and exportation ſhall be payed to the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Life-renters and others, from whom the Marchant export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers bought theſe Salmond, they alwayes producing Certificates from the reſpective Heretors and others, making up the juſt quantities contained in their Entries; upon which Certificate, the foreſaid ſum of twelve pounds is to be payed, to the Heretors and others from whom theſe Salmond were bought, or to any haveing their warrant to receive the ſame; which ſums <hi>reſpectivé</hi> above-written, for the Herring, White-fiſh and Salmond, are to be payed in mannor above-ſpecified, by the Collectors at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Ports where the ſame ſhall be entered, for whom, the Farmers and principal Collectors of the Exciſe are to be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and careful that the ſame ſhall be punctually payed; and in caſe of not punctual payment, they ſhall be lyable for the parties damage; providing alwayes, that the ſaid Herring, White-fiſhes and Salmond, be duly entered in the Exciſe-office, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation thereof ſufficiently inſtructed to the Collectors, ſo as they may certifie the ſame under their hands. Likeas, His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, doth inhibite and diſcharge the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors or Farmers of Exciſe upon any pretext, to give any eaſe or abatement of the fourty ſhillings <hi>Scots</hi> impoſed by the foreſaid fourteen Act, upon ilk Bool of forraign Bay-ſalt, <hi>Linlithgow</hi>-meaſure, imported into this Kingdom: Certifying them, if they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33954:13"/>contraveen, the ſaids Collectors ſhal ſuffer deprivation of their Office, and the ſaids Farmers ſhall looſe the benefit of their Tack of the Exciſe, and ſhall be further lyable to the payment of ſuch fines and penalties, as the Lords of Exchequer ſhall think fit to inflict. And for the better inbringing of the Exciſe of the ſaid In-land Salt, it is Ordained, that all Owners of Salt-pans and their Greeves, ſhall be obliged to exhibite and produce to the Collectors or Farmers of Exciſe or their Deputies, when they ſhall be required, their Compt-book of all Salt ſold, to be peruſed by them, and returned within the ſpace of twenty four hours, to the effect, it may be known what Salt is conſumed, and that the Exciſe of the ſame is duely payed, whereupon they are to make faith, if they be required, and that they have ſold nor diſpoſed upon no more nor is contained in the ſaid Books; And ſicklike, the Saltars of every Salt-pan ſhall be oblieged to give an account to the Collectors of the ſaid Exciſe of the Salt appertaining to them any manner of way, and what they have ſold of the ſame, and to inſtruct, that the ſame hath been duely entred in the Exciſe-office, and that the Exciſe duty of the ſame hath been payed, whereupon, and that they have ſold no more but what hath been duely entred, they are Ordained to make faith if they be required; It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes provided, that where Exciſe-offices are in the Town or place where the Salt is made, the Salt-maſters, their Greeves or Salters, ſhall be holden to repair to the Exciſe-office, to the effect foreſaid, if they be required; but if there be no Exciſe-office in theſe places, the Collectors or Farmers of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe or their Deputies are appointed to conveen them at the reſpective Salt Girnals, or Salt-pans where the Salt is made, and the ſaids perſons ſhall not be oblieged to go any further. And in like manner, His <hi>Majesty</hi> conſidering, that divers queſtions and debates may ariſe, anent the interpretation of ſeveral Acts and Priviledges made and granted in favours of Manufactories, for immunity and exemption from the Exciſe or Cuſtom of certain Goods, which are the Materials of the ſaid Manufactories; Doth hereby, with conſent foreſaid, Statute, Ordain and Declare, That no Manufactory ſhall have the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereof, excepting ſuch as ſhall be, or hath been law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully erected ſince the firſt day of <hi>January,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred ſixty one years, and ſhall be found by the Lords of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Exchequer to have been, or to be erected con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Acts of Parliament, and to have the qualifications required by the ſame. And further, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that if after ſo large expreſſions of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royal care and tenderneſs for the advancement of Trade and eaſe of Merchants, any ſhall be ſo unfaithful as to perſume to conceal and abſtract the Goods imported by them, thereby evading
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33954:14"/>the payment of the Cuſtom and Exciſe due and payable to His <hi>Majeſty;</hi> not only His <hi>Majeſty</hi> will be prejudged of His Cuſtom and Exciſe, but alſo the Trade of Merchandiſe will be much endamaged by the ſaid Merchants their underſelling others, who do honeſtly make true entries of their Goods, and pay the duties of Cuſtom and Exciſe. Therefore, for preventing of the ſaid prejudice and abuſe, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, doth give power and warrand to the Collectors of Cuſtom and Exciſe, or to their Deputies, to call and purſue ſuch perſons who ſhall wilfully and wickedly conceal and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract their Goods, or any part thereof, and not duly enter the ſame, or who ſhall be acceſſory, or any wayes aiding and aſſiſting to the concealing or abſtracting thereof; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords of His <hi>Majecties</hi> Exchequer, if the ſaids perſons dwell and reſide within twelve miles of the place where the ſaids Lords ſhall happen to ſit for the time, or in their option, before any other competent Judge: And in caſe the ſaids perſons live at farther diſtance, it ſhall be lawful to the ſaid Collectors or Farmers, or their Deputies, to purſue them before the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, Stewarts of Stewartries, or Bailiffs of Regalities, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of Burghs, or any other competent Judges, who are hereby required to take due and ſpeedy tryal of the premiſſes, and to admit probation thereof by writ, witneſs, oath of party or otherwiſe according to Law, any Act or Acts of Parliament, or Clauſes therein contained to the contrary thereof notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. And to the end, that His <hi>Majesties</hi> Lieges and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, upon the occaſion and pretence foreſaid, be not unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moleſted and troubled, It is Ordained, that the ſaids Proceſs and Purſutes ſhall be intended within three Moneths af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fraudful abſtracting and imbezleing foreſaid; and that theſe at whoſe inſtance they ſhall be purſued, ſhall be oblieged to give their oaths <hi>de calumnia,</hi> if thereto required, that the ſaids purſutes are not intended of malice, but upon credible information, and that they have juſt reaſon to purſue, as they conceive. And in caſe any Merchant, Skipper, Mate or Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or other perſon ſhall be found guilty of, or acceſſory to, the ſaid imbezeling, in concealing or abſtracting any Goods which ought and ſhould have been entered; It is Statute and Ordained, that the ſaid delinquents ſhall be impriſoned for the ſpace of twenty four hours, and untill they make payment of the full price and value of the Goods which ſhall be found to have been abſtracted by them, and ſhall be further fined by the Lords of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Exchequer, as they ſhall ſee cauſe. And in caſe any Goods ſhall be found and ſeiſed, upon account that they were concealed and not duly entered, they ſhall not only be detained and confiſcate without redemption, but alſo the Owners of the ſaid Goods, and all others who ſhall be found
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33954:14"/>to be acceſſory or aiding to the concealing or abſtracting of the ſame, ſhall be impriſoned for the ſpace of twenty four hours, and ſuch fines and other puniſhment ſhall be impoſed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them, as the Lords of Exchequer ſhall appoint. And that the Collectors of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Cuſtoms and Exciſe and their Deputies, at the making their accounts of their intromiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with the Cuſtom and Exciſe-duties, ſhall be holden and obliged to give their oaths upon the truth of theſe accounts to be given in by them. And it is provided and declared by His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, that the foreſaid Act of His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> firſt Parliament, whereby the Exciſe is impoſed, ſhall ſtand, and is and ſhall be of full force; except in ſo far as the ſame is altered, innovat, qualified and taken away in manner above-mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="act">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:33954:15"/>
               <head>XIII. <hi>ACT for annexation of</hi> Orknay <hi>and</hi> Zet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>to the Crown</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 17. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the Iſles of <hi>Orknay</hi> and <hi>Zetland</hi> are a great and ſo conſiderable a part of this His <hi>Majeſties</hi> ancient Kingdom, that for divers Ages they were the occaſion of much trouble and expenſe of blood and money, for maintaining thereof againſt the invaſion of Forraigners, and recovering the ſame out of their hands by Arms and Treaties; And the ſaids Iſles being of a great and large extent of bounds, and ſo remote and at ſuch a diſtance from the ordinary ſeat of Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice and Judicatories, that the Inhabitants within the ſame are not able to travel in the winter ſeaſon; and at other times can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, without great trouble and expenſes, repair to the ſaid Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories to complain when they are oppreſſed and grieved. It is not only fit in order to His <hi>Majesties</hi> Intereſt, but will be the great advantage of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects dwelling there, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interpoſing any other Lord or Superior betwixt His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and them, they ſhould have an immediate dependance upon His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and His Officers, being their great ſecurity againſt For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign attempts and oppreſſion at home. And ſeing it is moſt expedient and neceſſar, that a publick Patrimony and certain Revenue in Lands, Lordſhips and others, ſhould be ſettled upon, and annexed unto His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Crown, for ſupporting of His Royal Eſtate and Government, and the great and neceſſar charges of the ſame, which if not defrayed out of His <hi>Majesties</hi> own Property and Revenue, would unavoidably ly, and be a heavy burden upon His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Lieges: And to that purpoſe, divers Acts of Annexation have been made from time to time, and in ſpecialy the Earldom of <hi>Orknay</hi> and Lordſhip of <hi>Zetland,</hi> with the pertinents of the ſame, were annexed to the Crown in the years, one thouſand five hundred and forty, and one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twelve, <hi>reſpective.</hi> And yet, importunity prevailing with His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and His Royal Father, their goodneſs and inclination to gratifie their Subjects, they have been induced to give away and part with ſo great a Jewel of their Crown, and to diſpone and grant Rights of the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip; which being found to be to the great prejudice of His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> His Crown and Subjects, and contrary to the Laws and Acts of Parliament of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33954:15"/>this Kingdom, by a Decreet of the Lords of Seſſion, obtained upon the twenty fifth day of <hi>February</hi> laſt by-paſt, at the inſtance of Sir <hi>John Nisbet</hi> of <hi>Dirletoun</hi> Knight, His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Advocat, for His <hi>Majeſties</hi> intereſt, againſt <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Morton, Charles</hi> Lord <hi>Dalkeith</hi> his ſon, <hi>George</hi> Viſcount of <hi>Grandiſtoun,</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain other perſons therein mentioned; the ſaids Lords by their Decreet foreſaid, have reduced the Contracts, Diſpoſitions, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feftments, Acts of diſſolution, and other Rights therein men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, made and granted by His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and his Royal Father, to, and in favours of, the diſeaſed <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Morton,</hi> Grandfather to <hi>William</hi> now Earl of <hi>Mortoun,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>George</hi> Viſcount of <hi>Grandiſtoun,</hi> of the ſaid Earldom of <hi>Orknay</hi> and Lordſhip of <hi>Zetland,</hi> with the Rights alſo therein mentioned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending thereupon: And the ſaids Lords have found and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that His <hi>Majesty</hi> hath good and undoubted Right to the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip, as His annexed property, for the reaſons therein contained; as the ſaid Decreet at length proports. Therefore, His <hi>Majesty,</hi> with advice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, doth Ratifie and Confirm the ſaid Decreet, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains the ſame to be of full force, ſtrength and effect in all time coming; holding and willing this their Ratification to be alsſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and effectual, as if the ſaid Decreet and whole tenor of the ſame were inſert herein. And His <hi>Majesty,</hi> following the laudable example and practice of His Royal Predeceſſors, doth, with conſent foreſaid, Ratifie the ſaid former Annexation of the ſame to the Crown; and without prejudice thereof, doth of new again unite, annex and incorporate to His Crown of this His an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Kingdom, to remain inſeparably with the ſame in all time coming, the ſaid Earldom of <hi>Orknay</hi> and Lordſhip of <hi>Zetland,</hi> with all and ſundry Iſles, Holmes, Udal-lands and other Lands whatſoever, of what name and by what deſignation ſoever the ſame are or may be known, lying within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Ork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay</hi> and pertaining to the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip, and belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in manner foreſaid, in Property or Superiority, or by any other Right or Title, together with all Caſtles, Towers, Fortalices, Milns, Multars, Fiſhings, Annual-rents, Reverſions, Patronages of Kirks, and Teinds Parſonage and Vicarage per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> within the bouds foreſaid; And all and whatſoever Mines of Gold, Silver, Copper and other Minerals within the foreſaid bounds, with the heretable Office of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciary, Sheriffship and Foudrie and Admiralty within the foreſaid Iſles, and belonging to the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip, with all other Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents, Caſualities, Priviledges, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſelictions, Offices and others whatſoever pertaining to the ſame; All which, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, doth unite and annex to His Crown, Declaring the generality foreſaid to be ſufficient to the intent and effect foreſaid, as if each Part, Parcel, Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33954:16"/>Office, Patronage or Priviledge belonging to the ſaid Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Lordſhip were herein exprrſt. And it is Statute and Declared, That the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip, Lands, Teinds, and others above-mentioned, annexed to the Crown in manner foreſaid, ſhall remain therewith in all time coming; and that the ſame or any part thereof ſhall nor, not may be given away in Fee and Heretage, nor in Frank-tenement, Life-rent, Penſion or Tack, except for the full duty which may be gotten from, and payed by the Tennents, nor by any other manner of Alienation, Right or Diſpoſition whatſoever, to any perſon or perſons of whatſoever eſtate, degree or quality they be, without advice, Decreet and Deliberation of the whole Parliament; and for great weighty and reaſonable cauſes concerning the good, welfare and publick intereſt of the whole Kingdom, firſt to be propoſed and to be adviſed, and maturely pondered and conſidered by the Eſtates, <hi>re integra,</hi> before any previous Grant, Right or Deed be given, made or done by His <hi>Majeſty</hi> or His Succeſſors, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diſpoſition of the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip or any part thereof, which may any wayes predetermine them or the Eſtates of Parliament, and prejudge the freedom of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation and Conſent. And if at any time hereafter it ſhall be thought fit to diſpone or grant any Right of any part of the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip, It is Declared, that the general nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of good ſervices, weighty cauſes and conſiderations ſhall not be ſufficient; but the particular cauſes and conſiderations whereupon His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and His Succeſſors may be induced to grant, and the Eſtates to conſent to ſuch Rights, are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt; that it may appear, that the ſame is not granted through importunity, or upon private ſuggeſtions or pretences, but for true, juſt and reaſonable cauſes and conſiderations of publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment. And farther, it is Declared, that if any general Act of Diſſolution of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> property ſhall be made at any time hereafter; The ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip, and others above-mentioned and annexed, ſhallnot be underſtood to fall or be comprehended under the ſame; And if the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip, or any part thereof, ſhall be annallied or diſponed, or any Right of the ſame ſhall be granted otherwayes then is appointed and ordained in manner above-mentioned; His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, doth ſtatute and declare, That all Diſpoſitions, Infeſtments and other Rights of the ſaid Earldom and Lordſhip, or any part thereof which ſhall be granted contrary to this preſent Act, with all Acts of diſſolution and Ratification and other Acts of Parliament concerning the ſame, ſhall be from the beginning and in all time coming void and null, and of no effect: And notwithſtanding thereof, that it ſhall be lawful to our Soveraign Lord and His Succeſſors for the time, to take back and receive at their pleaſure for their own uſe, without any
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33954:16"/>Proceſs of Law, the Lands and others above-annexed, or any part thereof which ſhall be annallied or diſponed; and theſe in whoſe favours any ſuch Rights and Alienations ſhall be made, ſhall be countable for, and lyable to refound and pay all profits, intromiſſion or benefit taken, uplifted or enjoyed by them in the mean time: And it is Declared, That all other Clauſes, Articles and Proviſions contained in any former Act or Acts of Annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to the advantage of His <hi>Majesty</hi> and His Crown, are and ſhall be holden as repeated and inſert herein. And farther, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of the Eſtates foreſaid, hath ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the ſaid Office of Sheriffship, and hath erected, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by erects a Stewartry within the bounds foreſaid of the ſaid Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Lordſhip, and Iſles of <hi>Orknay</hi> and <hi>Zetland,</hi> to be called in all time coming, <hi>The Stewartry of Orknay and Zetland;</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining the Tenents, Poſſeſſors and Inhabitants within the bounds foreſaid, and other perſons who were formerly anſwerable and lyable to the juriſdiction of Sheriffship and Foudrie above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, to be anſwerable to His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Stewart of the ſaid Stewartry, with all Priviledges competent to any Stewartry of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Property within this Realm. Likeas, it is Declared and Statute, that the foreſaid Office of Stewartry ſhall not be given heretably to any perſon or perſons and their heirs, without advice and conſent of Parliament in manner above mentioned; and all Rights of the ſame which ſhall be granted otherwayes at any time hereafter, ſhal be from the beginning and in all time coming null and void. It is alwayes Declared, that this Act and Annexation foreſaid ſhall not prejudge the Biſhop of <hi>Orknay</hi> of his Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Priviledges belonging to him, or of any part thereof; and that he and his Succeſſors ſhall be in the ſame caſe as they were before the making hereof. And likewayes it is Declared, that the Annexation foreſaid and the ſuppreſſing of the ſaid Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Sheriff, and the erecting of the ſaid Stewartry ſhall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Vaſſals within the ſaid Iſles, of their Liberty and Priviledge to have and ſend Commiſſioners to Parliament, to repreſent them in the ſame manner as they did or might have done formerly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="act">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33954:17"/>
               <head>XIV. <hi>ACT concerning the exportation of Corns.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 17. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord conſidering, that by the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Act of the third Seſſion of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> late Parliament, liberty is granted to export Corns of all ſorts, when they are under the prices following, <hi>viz.</hi> Ilk Boll of Wheat under twelve pounds the Boll, Beer and Barley under eight pounds the Boll, Oats and Peaſe under eight merks the Boll. And ſeeing, by reaſon of ſeveral Duties formerly impoſed upon Corns, the exportation thereof hath been hitherto obſtructed; And his <hi>Majeſty</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous for the good of this His ancient Kingdom, to give all due en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the export of Corns, and to remove every thing which may impede the ſame: Hath therefore thought fit, Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of His Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, doth Statute and Declare, That all Corns which ſhall be exported in time coming by His <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſubjects forth of this Kingdom, ſhall be free, and are hereby diſcharged of the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Cuſtom, Bullion, and all other Duties whatſoever, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one Merk <hi>ſcots</hi> allenerly for ilk Chalder. And leſt any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable prejudice ſhould thereby enſue to His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, it is Statute and Ordained, That the Duties after-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are and ſhal be impoſed upon the Commodities following, <hi>viz.</hi> Ten ſhillings <hi>ſcots</hi> upon ilk Barrel of Tar, and twenty ſhillings <hi>ſcots</hi> upon ilk Tun of Iron imported into this Kingdom, and that over and above all former Impoſitions put thereon; and the Cuſtomers, Collectors and their deputies are hereby appointed and impowered to uplift the ſame accordingly. And for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting any debates that may ariſe anent the reſpective prices of the Victual, when the ſame are under or above the rates expreſt in the ſaid Act; His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, doth recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to, and authorizeth the Lords of Privy Council to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſame; And Declares, that it ſhall be lawful to His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties</hi> Subjects to export Corns of all ſorts, unleſs by a Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or publick Intimation from the ſaids Lords of Council, they be prohibited and diſcharged to do the ſame. And Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains this Act to begin and take effect upon the ſecond day of <hi>February</hi> next to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="act">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33954:17"/>
               <head>XIV. <hi>ACT for regulating the prices of Ale and Drinking-beer, and Maltmen.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 23. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord conſidering that it is moſt agreeable to reaſon and equity, and of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal concernment to all His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects, and ſpecially to thoſe of the meaner ſort, that a due proportion be obſerved betwixt the price of the Boll of Beer, and the Pint and other meaſures of Ale and Drinking-Beer vented and ſold within this Kingdom, that thereby the liberty taken by Brewars and Vintners, to exact exorbitant prices for Ale and Drinking-beer at their pleaſure may be reſtrained. Therefore His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of His Eſtates of Parliament, doth recommend to, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize the Lords of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Privy Council from time to time, after conſideration had of the ordinary rates of Rough-Beer and Barley for the time, to regulate and ſet down the prices of all Ale and Drinking-Beer, vented and ſold in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Shires and Burghs of the Kingdom, as they ſhall think juſt and reaſonable; And likewayes to ſet down a Table of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt the weight and price of all Bread made of Wheat, and the price of the Boll of Wheat, in like maner as betwixt the price of the Ale and the Boll of Beer: With power to the ſaids Lords of Council to make and emit ſuch Acts, Orders and Directions, in relation to the prices of Ale and Drinking-Beer, and weight and prices of Wheat-bread, and to inflict ſuch cenſures, pains and penalties upon the contraveeners of theſe Acts and Orders as they ſhall think fit; and to do all other things requiſite for execution of the ſame. And in caſe, after ſettling of the ſaids prices by the Lords of Council, any Brewar ſhall ceaſe from, and give over their brewing or venting of Ale or Beer, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, Declares, that they ſhall not be permitted or allowed to brew or vent any Ale or Beer for the ſpace of one year thereafter, and ſhal be further lyable to ſuch pains and puniſhments, as the Lords of Council ſhall think fit. And further, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> taking to conſideration, that by the twenty ninth Act of the firſt Parliament of King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth, Maltmen are declared to be no Craft, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged to have a Deacon; Which Act of Parliament, His
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33954:18"/>
                  <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid Ratifies and Approves, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains the ſame to ſtand in full force and effect in all time coming. And that notwithſtanding of the ſaid Act, and expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trair thereto, The Provoſt and Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> have, by their Act dated the eleventh of <hi>March,</hi> one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fourty ſix, ranked Maſtmen amongſt one of their Trades and Callings, diſcharged any to be admitted thereto within their B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ony of <hi>Leith,</hi> but by their Licence, with conſent of the Calling; and have conſtitute a Box-maſter amongſt them, and granted liberty to them to meet and keep correſpondence, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Water-Bailiff be preſent with them: Therefore, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and Eſtates of Parliament not only Declares the ſaid pretended Act of the Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to have been null and void from the beginning, and Ordains the ſame to be razed out of their Regiſters; but diſcharges the ſaid Town, or any other Burgh within the Kingdom, ever to preſume to do the like again; And Ordains the ſaid Box to be broken, and the Office of Deacon, Viſitor, Box-maſter, or any other pretending to the like power, and the pretended Calling or Incorporation and Society of Brewars or Maltmen, to ceaſe at <hi>Leith,</hi> and in all other Burghs, Towns and Places in the Kingdom: With certification, that if they ſhall be found hereafter to meet and keep correſpondence amongſt themſelves, upon whatſoever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, either at <hi>Leith, Edinburgh,</hi> or in any other Burgh, Town or Place, ilk perſon ſo meeting ſhal be lyable in the penalty of five hundred Merks <hi>toties quoties,</hi> whereof the one half to be payed to the informer, he proving the ſame before the Council; and this by and attour ſuch perſonal puniſhment, as the Lords of Privy Council ſhall think fit to inflict.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="act">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33954:18"/>
               <head>XVI. <hi>ACT for repairing High-wayes and Bridges.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 23. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord conſidering how neceſſar it is for the good of the people, that High-wayes be made and maintained for ready and eaſie Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, Travel and Traffick through the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that the care thereof which hath been laid upon the Juſtices of Peace, hath yet for the moſt part proven ineffectual, in regard the ſaids Juſtices have not had ſpecial Orders and Warrands for that effect. For remeid whereof, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, Doth Appoint and Ordain the Sheriff of the Shire, and one of his Deputies, being alwayes an Heretor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and the Juſtices of Peace in each Shire, to conveen at the head Burgh of the Shire upon the firſt Tueſday of <hi>May</hi> yearly, for ordering of High-wayes, Bridges and Ferries; With power to them, or major part of them that ſhall happen to conveen, to ſet down a particular Liſt of the High-wayes, Bridges and Ferries within their bounds, and to divide the Paroches of the ſaids bounds as they lye moſt to the ſeveral High-wayes to be repaired, and as they may have the moſt equal burden, and to appoint ſuch of their number or other Overſeers of ſuch parts and portions of the ſaids High-wayes, as are moſt convenient and neareſt to their ordinary reſidence, and to nominate ſuch of their number as they ſee fit, to ſurvey and give an account of the High-wayes, Bridges and Ferries unto the reſt; with power to them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Meetings from time to time, till the ſaid Survey, Liſt and Diviſion of the ſaids High-wayes be cloſed: Which perſons, or any one of them to whom the particular portions of the ſaids High-wayes ſhall be committed, are hereby authorized and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required, to call and conveen all Tennants and Cottars and their Servants, within the bounds appointed for their parts of the High-wayes, by publick intimation at the Paroch-Kirks upon the Sabbath day, immediatly after the firſt Sermon, or any other way that they ſhall think fit, to have in readineſs Horſes, Carts, Sleds, Spades, Shovels, Picks, Mattocks, and ſuch other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments as ſhall be required, for repairing of the ſaids High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, and to conveen at ſuch places thereof as they ſhal be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and in ſuch proportion and with ſuch furniture as the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33954:19"/>ſaids Juſtices or Overſeers ſhall appoint, and that in the moſt equal and proportionable way, as the ſaids Juſtices and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers will be anſwerable. With power to them to deſign ſuch of the ſaids perſons as they find to be moſt skillful, to attend and direct the reſt, and to appoint them fit Wages for their attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; providing that the dayes they are required to work do not exceed the number of ſix dayes for Man and Horſe yearly for the firſt three years, and four dayes yearly thereafter, and that they be only betwixt the Bear-ſeed yearly, and Hay-time or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thereafter: With power to the ſaids Juſtices or Overſeers to poind the readieſt Goods of the abſents, for twenty ſhillings <hi>Scots</hi> money for the abſence of ilk Man daily, and thirty ſhillings for the Man and Horſe, without further ſolemnity but appriſing the ſame upon the ground of the Land, and therewith to hire others in place of the abſents; and in caſe the ſaids abſents ſhall have no poindable Goods, to puniſh them in their perſons as they ſhall ſee cauſe. Which High-wayes ſhall be twenty foot of meaſure broad at leaſt, or broader, if the ſame have been ſo of before, and ſhall be ſo repaired, that Horſes and Carts may travel Summer and Winter thereupon: and if any part of the ſaids High-wayes cannot well be continued as now they are, but require to be changed, the ſaids Juſtices ſhall appoint three of their number to viſit the places where the High-wayes need to be changed, and to ſet down Meiths for the new Way in place thereof, and upon Oath to eſtimate the damage of the parties prejudged thereby, and to deliver the ſame to them in writing under their hands, to the effect the ſame may be ſatisfied by the whole Shire, in manner after-ſpecified. Which Juſtices are Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained again to conveen at the head Burgh of the Shire the firſt Tueſday of <hi>June</hi> yearly, and thence every Tueſday from fourt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night to fourtnight, at ſuch places as ſhal be by them appointed during the Moneths of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> for three years next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, for taking account of the ſaid ſeveral Juſtices and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers of the reſpective proportions of High-way committed to them, and to fine thoſe Juſtices and Overſeers who ſhal failȝie; ſtill increaſing the ſaids fines till they give obedience and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their part, and to poind therefore upon the ground of the Lands where their Goods ſhall be found, without further ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. With power alſo to the ſaids Juſtices to viſit the Ferries in their Shire, and where the Ferries ly betwixt two Shires, that they correſpond with the Juſtices of the other Shire, to the end they may appoint fit and ſufficient Boats, and convenient Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places; and ſo to regulate all things concerning the Ferries, as His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Lieges may be readily and conveniently ſerved, and at reaſonable rates, and to puniſh all ſuch as ſhall neglect or tranſgreſs the Rules ſet down by them to the effect foreſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33954:19"/>And becauſe the work of the inhabitants within the ſeveral bounds, will not be able ſufficiently to repair the High-wayes and others foreſaid; Therefore, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the ſaid Eſtates, doth hereby authorize and require the whole Free-holders and Heretors of the ſeveral Shires, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veen at the reſpective head Burghs the ſaid firſt Tueſday of <hi>June</hi> yearly, and to call for an accompt from the Juſtices of Peace of what is needful for reparation of the High-wayes and others fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and what charges and expenſes is requiſite for promoving thereof; and for making or repairing Bridges and Ferries where they ſhall be found needful, and accordingly to ſtent the Heretors of the ſaid Shire, comprehending the Heretors of the Burrough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands therein, in what ſhall be found neceſſary for the effect fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, not exceeding ten ſhillings <hi>Scots</hi> upon each hundred pound of valued Rent in one year, which is to be uplifted be the ſaids Juſtices or whom they ſhall appoint, be poinding as ſaid is, and imployed for the uſe foreſaid; and of which they ſhall be oblieged to give an accompt to the ſaids Heretors at the next <hi>Michaelmas</hi> head Court yearly. Likeas, His <hi>Majesty,</hi> with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent foreſaid, prohibits and diſcharges all perſons whatſoever to break or abuſe the ſaids High-wayes by plowing up any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, laying ſtones, rubbiſh or dung thereon, or any way breaking or pooling the ſame, or turning in, or damming water thereupon; and Ordains the Conveener of the ſaids Juſtices at their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid firſt Tueſday of <hi>May</hi> yearly, to take an Oath of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Juſtices and of the Conſtables, of what damage they know done to the High-wayes, Bridges or Ferries ſince the year preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in any of the foreſaid particulars prohibited, or any other, and by whom. Upon which, the ſaids Juſtices ſhall conveen the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors and in caſe of conviction by oath or witneſs, ſhal fine them as they ſhal ſee juſt, and ſhall poind therefore in manner foreſaid, and apply the ſame for the uſe of the ſaids High-wayes. With power alſo to the ſaid Juſtices, to call for an accompt of all Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and Mortifications to Bridges, Cauſa's, Ferries or High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, and to cauſe the intrometters therewith, that have not applyed the ſame to theſe proper ends, to make payment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to ſuch perſons as they ſhall appoint, to be imployed to the uſes for which the ſame were deſtinat. Likeas, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains the Conveener of the ſaids Juſtices to give a particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt under his hand, of what progreſs is made in the repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaids High-wayes, Ferries and Bridges, upon the third Tueſday of <hi>July</hi> next to come, and ſo forth yearly to the Lords of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Privy Council, who are hereby impowered to grant Letters of Horning and Poinding for the effects fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid if need be.</p>
               <p>And further, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with conſent foreſaid, gives power to the ſaids Lords of His <hi>Majesties</hi> Privy Council, to Ordain the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33954:20"/>levying of moderat Cuſtoms at Bridges, Cauſa's or Ferries for the building, repairing and upholding thereof, in caſe the ſaids Stent ſhall not be able to accompliſh the ſame, and to appoint the endurance thereof as they ſhal ſee cauſe. With power alſo to them, that in caſe the ſaids Juſtices and Heretors failȝie in the performance of the things by this Act committed to them, ſo that the High-wayes ſhall not be ſufficiently repaired, nor Bridges and Ferries ſufficiently provided for, to take ſuch courſe for making the ſame effectual as they ſhall judge expedient, and to puniſh the ſaids Heretors and Juſtices, as their neglect ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve: With power likewayes to the ſaids Lords of Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, to appoint and commiſſionat Overſeers for putting the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes in execution where they ſhall ſee cauſe; which Overſeers ſo appointed, ſhall have the ſame power as is by this preſent Act committed to the Juſtices of Peace foreſaid. And farther, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> Ordains, that where laboured Land lyes upon the ſides of High-wayes, the ſaid laboured Land ſhall be fenced with Dike and Ditch or Hedge; yet ſo as neither Dike, nor Ditch, nor Hedge, nor any part thereof, be within the forementioned breadth appointed for the High-way: And in caſe any laboured Land ſo lying ſhal not be fenced betwixt and the firſt day of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and ſeventy one, then and in that caſe, the ſaids Juſtices are hereby authorized and required to cauſe poind in manner foreſaid, the Labourers of the ſaid Land for four ſhillings <hi>Scots</hi> for each eln which ſhall not be ſo fenced after the ſaid time, and to apply the ſaid fines for the fencing thereof in manner foreſaid. Likeas, it is hereby Declared, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſtones, rubbiſh, dung or other impediments beis thrown or found lying upon the ſaids High-wayes, or water turned in or dammed thereupon, ſhall be eſteemed and held as done by the Labourers of the Land next adjacent to the High-wayes where the damage is done, who ſhal be fined therefore be the ſaid Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ices and Overſeers; Reſerving right to the ſaids Labourers to call before the ſaids Juſtices any other for their relief, who have been the real actors of the skaith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="act">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:33954:20"/>
               <head>XVII. <hi>ACT anent incloſing of Ground.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 23. 1669</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas by the fourty one Act of the firſt Seſſion of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> firſt Parliament, entituled, <hi>Act for planting and incloſing of Ground,</hi> It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that where Incloſers fall to be upon the borders of any mans Inheritance, the next ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Heretor ſhal be at equal pains and charges in building, ditching, and planting that Dike which divides their Inheritance. And the Eſtates of Parliament conſidering the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency and difficulty the execution of that part of the ſaid Act may meet with, in Lands marching together where the Marches are crooked and unequal, or where any part of the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Ground is unfit or uncapable of bearing a Dike or receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Ditch, or hinders the compleating of the Incloſure in an equal line. For remeid whereof, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of the ſaid Eſtates, doth Statute and Ordain, That whenſoever any perſon intends to incloſe by a Dike or Ditch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the March betwixt his Lands and the Lands belonging to other Heretors contiguous thereunto; it ſhal be leiſome to him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the next Sheriffs or Bailiffs of Regalities, Stewarts of Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>artries, Juſtices of peace or other Judges Ordinar, to viſit the Marches alongſt which the ſaid Dike or Ditch is to be drawn, who are hereby authorized, when the ſaid Marches are uneven or otherwayes uncapable of Ditch or Dike, to adjudge ſuch parts of the one or other Heretors Ground, as occaſion the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency betwixt them, from the one Heretor in favours of the other, ſo as may be leaſt to the prejudice of either party, and the Dike or Ditch to be made, to be in all time thereafter the common March betwixt them; and the parts ſo adjudged <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective</hi> from the one to the other, being eſtimat to the juſt avail and compenſed <hi>pro tanto,</hi> to decern what remains uncompenſed of the price, to the party to whom the ſame is wanting: And it is hereby Declared, that the parts thus adjudged <hi>hinc inde,</hi> ſhall remain and abide with the Lands or Tennandries to which they are <hi>reſpective</hi> adjudged, as parts and pendicles thereof in all time coming.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="act">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:33954:21"/>
               <head>XVIII. <hi>ACT anent Adjudications.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 23. 1669</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord taking to conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that by ſeveral Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſtant Practick of the Kingdom, there is one years Rent of all Lands, Annual-rents or others ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, due and payable to the Superior of the ſaids Lands and others, before he be holden to enter and infeft the Compriſer; and that there is the ſame reaſon in caſes of Adjudications as Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſings. Therefore, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes, Ordains and Declares, That the Superiors of Lands, Annual-rents and others adjud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſhall not be holden to grant any Charter for infefting the Adjudger, till ſuch time as he be payed and ſatisfied of the years Rent of the Lands and others adjudged, in the ſame manner as in Compriſings; And Declares, that in all caſes, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judications ſhall be in the like condition with Compriſings, as to Superiours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="act">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:33954:21"/>
               <head>XIX. <hi>ACT concerning the Confirmation and Quots of Teſtaments.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 23 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord, with advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and Ordains, That it ſhal be lawful to Executors, at the confirmation of the Defuncts Teſtament, to give up the Debts owing be the Defunct, and that the Quot be only payed for the free Geer (the Debts being always inſtructed) with power to the ſaids Executors, for inſtructing of the ſaids Debts before the Commiſſar the time of Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to cite the Creditors for production of the Bonds and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of their ſaids Debts; and if the ſaids Creditors ſhall not produce the ſame, and yet ſhall happen thereafter to ſeek payment from the Executors, that then and in that caſe, the Creditors ſhall be oblieged to relieve the Executors of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the Quot payed by them, effeiring to the ſaid Debt, or otherwayes to allow the ſame to them; And for preventing of all fraud, both the Executors and Creditors ſhall be holden to make faith, if required, anent the truth and reality of the ſaids Debts, that they were truly reſting unſatisfied the time of the Defuncts deceaſe. And likewayes, Statutes and ordains, That in all time coming, Executors Creditors be free of paying of Quot, in ſo far as they confirm only for Debts reſting to them be the Defunct the time of his deceaſe, and thereupon the ſaids Executors ſhall be holden to make faith, if required, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of any Inſtruction produced by them. As alſo, the Relict confirming her ſelf Executrix Creditrix, and for ſatisfying of the obliegement of her Contract of Marriage; or other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made to her by her Huſband where there was no Contract of Marriage, be alſo free of Quot, in ſo far as the Inventar ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to five years purchaſe of the Annual-rent or Life-rent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to her; and that ſhe ſhall be lyable and pay Quot for the <hi>ſuperplus</hi> of the free Goods or Debts confirmed; And that this be extended to all other Life-renters, confirming themſelves Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors Creditors. As likewayes, that poor people, not worth in heretable or moveable Eſtate fourty pounds <hi>Scots</hi> money, have their Confirmation paſt and regiſtrat free from payment of any Quot; and for Fees of Court, that they pay only two pounds eighteen ſhillings <hi>Scots.</hi> And farther, it is Statute and Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That heretable Debts reſting by the Defunct, be Infeſtment, Bonds or Contracts bearing obliegement to infeſt, be not allowed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33954:22"/>be the Commiſſars at the Confirmation, to defaulk off the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar in prejudice of the Quot, where there is an heretable Eſtate belonging to the Defunct to ſatisfie the heretable Debts, even though the ſaids Debts be given up by the Defunct himſelf or his Executor. And likewayes, it is Statute and Ordained, that Commiſſars admit of no diviſion in Teſtaments, in favours and upon accompt of the Relict, where by her Contract of Marriage or otherwayes, ſhe is ſecluded from all part of her Huſbands move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables; And if a bipartit or tripartit diviſion be craved be the Executor at the confirmation upon her accompt, in that caſe the Procurator Fiſcal ſhal have power to cite the Relict, for producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Contract of Marriage, or to give Oath upon her hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, or that by the ſame or any other Writ, ſhe is ſecluded: And if it appear, either be the ſaid Contract or be any other Writ, or be the Relicts Oath, that ſhe is ſecluded from the third or half of the moveables, That then the Teſtament ſhall be confirmed without diviſion upon her accompt, and the Quot payed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; And in caſe there be any exception in the Relicts favours, of the Inſight and Houſhold-pleniſhing, or any part thereof, in that caſe deduction is only to be granted of the quot, effeiring to the proportion excepted and reſerved in her favours. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice foreſaid, Statutes and Ordains, that in time coming, no Charges of Horning be given to any perſon, at the Procurator Fiſcals inſtance, for giving up of Inventer, but upon a Roll of the perſons names to be charged ſubſcribed be the Commiſſar, and that within the ſpace of three years after the Defuncts deceaſe, after which time it ſhall not be leiſome to give any ſuch Charges of Horning for giving up of Inventer; And for the years preceeding, that they ſhal only charge for giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Inventer of the Goods of ſuch Defuncts who have deceaſt ſince the year, one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty. And Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, That Letters of Caption ſhall not be uſed againſt any of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Lieges for not confirming of Teſtaments, but where the Letters of Horning have been execute againſt the parties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally, or at their Dwelling-houſes and Paroch-Kirk-doors, on a Sabbath-day after Divine Service. And Ordains the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſars of the reſpective Dioceſſes, to keep Circuit Courts the time of the Spring and Harveſt Vacance, for confirmation of Teſtaments at ſuch convenient places in ilk Preſbytery, as may be moſt conducing to the good and eaſe of the Lieges; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are to be cited perſonally, or at their Dwelling-places and Paroch-Kirks as ſaid is, to the end and effect foreſaid: With certification, that if the Commiſſar, Commiſſar-clerk, Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Fiſcal, or any other Member of Court, contraveen this Act, the contraveener ſhall ſuffer deprivation of his Office, and never be re-admitted thereto again, beſide ſatisfaction to the party grieved, of any damage ſuſtained by him there-through.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="act">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33954:22"/>
               <head>XX. <hi>ACT for in-bringing of publick Dues from the Northern Shires.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 23. 1669</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord conſidering, that divers perſons within the Shires of <hi>Roſs, Sutherland, Caithneſs, Argyl, Inverneſs</hi> and Burghs within the ſame, are in arrear, and deficient in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a conſiderable part of the Annuity of Exciſe, granted to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in the year one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty one, the Taxation and aſſeſſment impoſed by the Conventions of Eſtates in the years, one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty five, and, one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty ſix-notwithſtanding of all legal diligence uſed for in-bringing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For obtaining payment of which Arears, and for the more effectual and better payment of the ſaid Annuity of Exciſe in time coming, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, doth Statute, Ordain and Declare, That the perſons deficient and in arrear of the foreſaid Annuity of Exciſe, Taxati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Aſſeſſment in the ſaid Shires, and Burghs within the ſame, preceeding the Moneth of <hi>November</hi> laſt, and who ſhal not pay in the ſame according to their reſpective proportions, to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and Collectors thereof, betwixt and the firſt day of <hi>June</hi> next to come, ſhal be lyable in double payment of all ſuch defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency and arrear, without any manner of defaulcation. And farther Declares, that if for the future, three quarters payment of the ſaid Annuity of Exciſe in the ſaid Shires, ſhall happen to run in the fourth unpayed (the feaſt and term of <hi>Candlemas</hi> next enſuing being the firſt terme) Then and in that caſe, ſuch Shires, Burghs and Perſons therein ſo deficient, ſhall be lyable in payment of the double of the whole years Annuity of Exciſe, <hi>toties quoties,</hi> and all execution perſonal and real ſhall be uſed againſt them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and Eſtates of Parliament doth hereby Declare, That this preſent Act or any thing therein contained, ſhall no wayes liberate the Commiſſioners of Exciſe for the ſaid reſpective Shires and Burghs, from being lyable in the ſingle pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment allanerly of the ſaid Annuity of Exciſe; but that they ſhall ſtill ſtand oblieged therefore as formerly, in maner contained in the Act of Parliament made thereanent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="act">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33954:23"/>
               <head>XXI. <hi>ACT</hi> Salvo jure cujuſlibet.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 23. 1669.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Soveraign Lord taking to conſideration, that there be many Acts of Ratifications and others, paſt and made in this Seſſion of Parliament, in favours of particular perſons, without calling or hearing of ſuch as may be thereby concerned and prejudged: Therefore, His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, That all ſuch particular Acts and Acts of Ratification paſt in maner foreſaid, ſhal not prejudge any third party of their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Rights, nor of their Actions and Defences competent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, before the making of the ſaid particular Acts and Acts of Ratifications; And that the Lords of Seſſion and all other Judges within this Kingdom, ſhall be oblieged to judge betwixt Parties, according to their ſeveral Rights ſtanding in their perſons before the making of the ſaids Acts: All which are hereby exponed, and Declared to have been made, <hi>Salvo jure cujuſlibet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="act">
               <head>XVII. <hi>ACT of Adjournment.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>December</hi> 23. 1669</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Kings <hi>Majeſty</hi> Declares this Parliament current, and adjourns the ſame to the eight of <hi>June</hi> next to come; Ordaining all the Members of Parliament to attend that day, and that there be no new Election of Commiſſioners from Shires or Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, except upon the Death of ſome of the preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_acts">
            <pb facs="tcp:33954:23"/>
            <head>A LIST of the Printed ACTS paſt in the PARLIAMENT, keeped at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in <hi>October,</hi> 1669.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>CT aſſerting His</hi> Majeſties <hi>Supremacy over all Perſons and in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> Page 3</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Act concerning the</hi> Militia. Page 5</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Act for regiſtration of Inſtruments of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation</hi> ad remanentiam. Page 9</item>
               <item>4. <hi>Act concerning poinding before the dayes of the Charge expire.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>Act for the ſecurity of the perſons of Miniſter-.</hi> Page 10</item>
               <item>6. <hi>Act for the ordering of Suſpenſions of the Benefices and Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends of the Clergy.</hi> Page 11</item>
               <item>7. <hi>Act for Naturalization of Strangers.</hi> Page 12</item>
               <item>8. <hi>Act concerning the Bullion.</hi> Page 14</item>
               <item>9. <hi>Act concerning preſciptions.</hi> Page 18</item>
               <item>10. <hi>Act concerning Interuptions.</hi> Page 19</item>
               <item>11. <hi>Act concerning the forfeiture of perſons in the late Rebellion.</hi> Page 20</item>
               <item>12. <hi>Act concerning the Exciſe and Cuſtoms.</hi> Page 22</item>
               <item>13. <hi>Act for annexation of</hi> Orknay <hi>and</hi> Zetland <hi>to the Crown.</hi> Page 28</item>
               <item>14. <hi>Act concerning the Exportation of Corns.</hi> Page 32</item>
               <item>15. <hi>Act for regulating the prices of Ale and Drinking-beer, and Maltmen.</hi> Page 33</item>
               <item>16. <hi>Act for repairing High-wayes and Bridges.</hi> Page 35</item>
               <item>17. <hi>Act anent incloſing of Ground.</hi> Page 39</item>
               <item>18. <hi>Act concerning adjudications.</hi> Page 40</item>
               <item>19. <hi>Act concerning the Confirmation and Quots of Testaments.</hi> Page 41</item>
               <item>20. <hi>Act for inbringing of publick Dues from the Northern Shires.</hi> Page 43</item>
               <item>21. <hi>Act</hi> Salvo jure cujuſlibet. Page 44</item>
               <item>22. <hi>Act of Adjournment.</hi> ibid.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_acts">
            <pb facs="tcp:33954:24"/>
            <head>A LIST of the Acts and Ratifications past in in this firſt Seſſion of His Majeſties ſecond Parliament, and which are not here printed.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>oteſtations by ſome Noblemen, and others Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners from Shires and Burghs, concerning their precedency in the Rolls of Parliament.</item>
               <item>His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Letters to the Parliament, concerning the Union of the Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> with the Parliaments Anſwers.</item>
               <item>Act anent the election of Commiſſioners from Shires.</item>
               <item>Act for continuing the Impoſition for upholding the Cauſſa of <hi>Couiemonth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Acts for yearly Fairs and Weekly Mercats to ſome Noblemen and others.</item>
               <item>Proteſtation by the Earl of <hi>Nithisdale,</hi> that the forfeiture of <hi>Mcklelland</hi> of <hi>Balmagachan</hi> ſhould not prejudge him.</item>
               <item>Proteſtation by the Vaſſals of <hi>Orknay,</hi> that they be not prejudged be the preſent annexation thereof to the Crown.</item>
               <item>Proteſtation in name of the Duke of <hi>Lenox,</hi> that this annexation do not prejudge his right of Admiralty in <hi>Orknay.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proteſtation by the Lord Advocate <hi>contra</hi> theſe two Proteſtations</item>
               <item>Commiſſion anent the regulation of the Commiſſar and Sheriff-Courts, and other inferiour Courts of Juſtice.</item>
               <item>Act ſuſpending the payment of publick Debts.</item>
               <item>Protection to <hi>William Dick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Hamiltoun.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proteſtation by the Town of <hi>Linlithgow</hi> againſt the ſame.</item>
               <item>Proteſtation by the Duke of <hi>Hamiltoun</hi> in the contrair.</item>
               <item>Two Ratifications in favours of the Earl of <hi>Argyl.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proteſtations be the Earl of <hi>Errol</hi> and others againſt the ſame.</item>
               <item>Proteſtation be the Earl of <hi>Argyl</hi> in the contrair.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Lord <hi>Newbyth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Mr. <hi>John Young</hi> of <hi>Leny.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>Thomas Moncrief</hi> of that ilk.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Earl of <hi>Kellie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Lord <hi>Stair.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> of <hi>Aberlady.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Mr. <hi>Andrew Oſwald</hi> and his Son.</item>
               <item>Two Ratifications in favours of Sir <hi>John Nicolſon</hi> of that ilk.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>Mungo Graham</hi> of <hi>Gorthie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Archbiſhop of St. <hi>Andrews.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33954:24"/>Ratification in favours of the Earl of <hi>Perth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Earl of <hi>Roxburgh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Alexander Frazer</hi> of <hi>Dorrs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Robert Cunningham</hi> of <hi>Achinharvy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>William Murray</hi> of <hi>Ochtertyre.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>James Drummond.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>John Forbes</hi> of <hi>Wattertoun.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proteſtation in name of the Town of <hi>Aberdeen</hi> againſt the ſame.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Earl of <hi>Tweedale.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Hary Bruce</hi> of <hi>Clackmannan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Alexander Don</hi> of <hi>Newtoun.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Patrick Home</hi> of <hi>Polwart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Charles Erskine</hi> of <hi>Cambo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification to him of his Office of <hi>Lyon King at Arms.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Philip Anſtruther.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>David Fothringhame</hi> of <hi>Pourie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Earl os <hi>Middleton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Earl of <hi>Dundonald.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Lord <hi>Lee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>John Keith</hi> of <hi>Caskieben.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Maſter of <hi>Roſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>John Forbes</hi> of <hi>Cullodin</hi> and his Son.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>David Blair</hi> of <hi>Adamtoun.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>William Hamiltoun</hi> of <hi>Wiſhaw.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>George Dundas</hi> of that ilk.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>William Ker</hi> of <hi>Hadden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>Thomas Boyd</hi> of <hi>Pinkill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Miniſter of North-<hi>Lieth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>Hugh Wat.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Town of <hi>Bervie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>Adam Blair</hi> of <hi>Carberry.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>George Fullertoun.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>David Philp</hi> of <hi>Overcarnbie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Mr. <hi>Robert Deens</hi> of <hi>Longhirdmiſtoun.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Earl of <hi>Annandale.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proteſtation in name of the Viſcount of <hi>Stormont</hi> againſt it.</item>
               <item>Proteſtation be the Earl of <hi>Annandale</hi> in the contrair.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>John</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Dalyells.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Mr. <hi>John Wiſhart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Earl of <hi>Linlithgow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>John Nisbet,</hi> Lord Advocat.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>Alexander Brodie</hi> of <hi>Letham, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>William Purveſs</hi> of <hi>Woodhouſlee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Girdle-makers of <hi>Culroſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of <hi>James Stewart</hi> of <hi>Torrence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33954:25"/>Ratification in favours of the Lord <hi>Drumlanrig.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Viſcount of <hi>Stormont.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Lieutenant-General <hi>Drummond.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>William Bruce</hi> of <hi>Balcaskie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the City of <hi>Glaſgow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proteſtation be the Town of <hi>Ruglin</hi> againſt it.</item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of the Town of <hi>Forfar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Mr. <hi>Andrew Burnet</hi> of <hi>Weriſtown.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratification in favours of Sir <hi>John Aitoun</hi> of that ilk.</item>
               <item>Remit for the Viſcounteſs of <hi>Stormant,</hi> Lord <hi>Drumlenrig</hi> and Laird of <hi>Ednem.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act for an Impoſition to be uplifted at the North-water Bridge.</item>
               <item>Prorogation of the Impoſition for the Bridge of <hi>Sauchtenhall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act for changing the Way at <hi>Walter Chieſties</hi> Houſe at <hi>Dalry.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Recommendation for the Heretors of the Sheriffdom of <hi>Berwick</hi> concerning their fiſhing on <hi>Tweed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commiſſions for the fiſhings in the Waters of <hi>Spey</hi> and <hi>Divern.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent the Fiſhings on <hi>Spey,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Commiſſion for improving of Trade.</item>
               <item>Act diſcharging the Cuſtom of Books.</item>
               <item>Act anent the Kirks of <hi>Kinneil</hi> and <hi>Burroughſtounneſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act concerning the Loſſes of the Town of <hi>Dundee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Recommendation in favours of the Maſters of the <hi>Scots</hi> Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration at <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Continuation of the Lady <hi>Bramfords</hi> buſineſs.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33954:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
